KYLE SHIPLEY

White City, OR 97503 559-750-8405 shipley.s.kyle@gmail.com

DATA-DRIVEN STRATEGIST | INNOVATIVE DATA SCIENTIST | IMPACTFUL PRODUCT OWNER

SUMMARY

Lead and managed data-driven solutions, from natural language processing programs to predictive model development, optimizing business operations and enhancing strategic insights. Extensive experience in Python, SQL, and data visualization tools like Power BI and Tableau.

NOTABLE ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Developed a natural language processing program that summarized technician and sales rep notes, significantly reducing manual effort.
- Built predictive models for monthly bonus pacing plans for dealerships, enhancing financial planning accuracy.
- Initiated a comprehensive data governance program to synchronize and document cross-departmental data sources, improving data integrity and accessibility.
- Created multiple executive dashboards for higher management, providing actionable insights and supporting strategic decision-making.

EXPERIENCE

Lithia & Driveway

Technical Product Owner • Medford, OR

05/2024 - 12/2024

Working closely with developers on project planning and execution, acting as a hybrid between technical and business roles. My responsibilities included managing the product backlog, utilizing Agile and Scrum methodologies, designing and managing APIs, employing DevOps practices, develop code, and creating comprehensive technical documentation, all while ensuring alignment with business goals and fostering stakeholder collaboration.

- Built models for predicting monthly bonus pacing plans for dealerships.
- Developed a natural language processing program summarizing technician and sales rep notes.
- Leverage extensive data science expertise to clean, process, and analyze dealership data using Python, Snowflake, TensorFlow, and Power BI.
- Initiated a data governance program to sync and document cross-departmental data sources and flows.
- Utilized Agile and Scrum methodologies, including sprint planning, daily stand-ups, and retrospectives.
- Designed, developed, and managed APIs to ingest multiple forms of data and translate the data formats via AI to generate SQL statements for insertion into databases, refining the AI to enhance precision.
- Employed DevOps practices to streamline development, testing, and deployment processes.

Senior Analyst • Medford, OR

01/2023 – 05/2024

Developed and maintained data collection programs to streamline processes and save time. I was heavily involved in creating dashboards for executives, providing valuable insights for decision-making. My role required me to lead project intake by scheduling and conducting meetings with stakeholders to understand and propose action plans for reporting needs. Collected, cleaned, and prepared large volumes of structured and unstructured data from various sources, ensuring the data was ready for analysis.

Developed programs to provide website and PDF data collection, saving over 700 hours a month.

- Developed multiple dashboards for higher managers and C-level executives.
- Led the intake process for project needs by scheduling meetings with stakeholders and proposing action plans for reporting needs
- Trained departments in small-scale reporting needs and facilitated handoff between teams.
- Collected, cleaned, and pipelined large amounts of structured and unstructured data from various sources and applications.

Data Science Analyst • Medford, OR

03/2022 - 01/2023

Their role involves cleaning, processing, and modeling data using various statistical and computational techniques. Developing algorithms, creating visualizations, and building predictive models to identify trends and patterns. Collaborated with stakeholders to understand business needs and provide actionable insights that drive strategy and improve operational efficiency.

- Developed a model in Python to automatically spot errors in a team's manual entry data, saving 25 hours a month.
- Tracked time series DMV data and produced dashboards to identify outliers for DMV processing fees, maintaining working relations in various states.
- Developed a program in Python to forecast sales for car makes and models by region using demographic DMV data.
- Generated actionable insights through the development of metrics and dashboards.
- Analyzed and extracted relevant information from large amounts of structured and unstructured data.

EDUCATION

Maryville University

Master of Data Science Data Science

2023-08

Brigham Young University

Bachelor of Science Studies Biology

2018-07

CERTIFICATIONS

Maryville University: Post Baccalaureate Certificate in Machine Learning, Maryville University

SKILLS

- Programming: Python (NumPy, Pandas, Scikit-learn, Matplotlib, Seaborn, PyTorch, TensorFlow), SQL, (Postgres, Snowflake), DAX, Power Automate, Alteryx, SAS, R.
- Machine Learning: Linear and Logistic Regressions, Gradient Boosted Decision Trees, Random, Forest, Support Vector Machines, K-Means Clustering, Principal Component Analysis, K-fold cross validation, LPO-cross-validation.
- Data Visualization: Power BI, Tableau.
- Product Ownership: Backlog management, Azure DevOps, release pipelines, Agile and Scrum methodologies.
- Technical Skills: API management, DevOps practices, technical documentation, user experience (UX) design
- Soft Skills: Stakeholder management, collaboration.